My name is John Kiriakou. I was a field
agent for the CIA. I hunted, tracked,
and captured terrorists around the world. This
is everything I'm authorized to tell you. I'm
not allowed to say how many officers or what
percentage of CIA officers are dedicated to
counterterrorism. After 9/11, the CIA became a
paramilitary organization. We started borrowing
special forces guys. They would be on
loan to the CIA to just fly somewhere,
kill somebody, and then fly back
for the next Tuesday meeting.
The most obvious risk of working as
a counterterrorism officer obviously
is the risk of death. There were two guys who I
worked with in CTC, the counterterrorism center,
Helge Boes, and Mike Spann, who were killed in
the line of duty. And it wasn't just them. I
was the chief of the counter intelligence branch
in the Osama bin Laden group. The woman that I
sat next to was killed in the line of duty in the
host bombing in Afghanistan. The suicide bomber,
he blew her and six of our colleagues up. So,
death, destruction, but on a on a an equally
personal note, your marriage is probably not going
to survive an operational tour in the director of
intelligence. The stress is just otherworldly.
It's the most difficult and dangerous thing
you can do as a CIA officer for a variety of
reasons. First, when people join terrorist groups,
they do that because they are true believers. And
in most cases, they hate you or what you stand for
more than they love life itself. And so, they are
very happy to die for a cause. At the same time,
if you're working counterterrorism issues,
you generally aren't doing it in London or
Paris or Ottawa. You're doing it in Yemen,
Somalia, Afghanistan, Pakistan, in Pakistan,
unless you were going to carry out an operational
act. You had to stay on the compound. It was just
simply too dangerous. And so, not only do you have
this exceedingly difficult job to do, but you have
to blend in and not attract attention to yourself
and keep yourself safe at the same time. I'll give
you an example. When I was stationed in Athens,
Athens was one of the most dangerous places in the
world for Americans, especially for American CIA
officers. 17 November had murdered the CIA station
chief, two US defense attaches, and a hapless
Air Force technical sergeant. This was a very,
very lethal group. And so, that was my primary job
to work against an incredibly deadly group. And I
was the go-to guy on Arab terrorism there because
I spoke Arabic. And I drove an armored car,
level four armor. I carried two guns. I had a
Glock 9mm on my waist and a Smith and Wesson 38 on
my ankle. Even kept a buck knife in my back pocket
just in case everything turned to that's all I
had left. Halfway through my tour, the British
embassy received a new defense attache. His name
was Steven Saunders. He was a one-star general,
brigadier general. Everybody loved him. Everybody
liked to be around him, the life of the party.
He loved being on camera. So, anytime you're at
some event and there's a camera, Steven would run
up to the camera and give an interview. Which is,
you know, great if you're not in a country that's
categorized as critical threat for terrorism. I
took delivery of this new BMW 540, fully armored.
And so we were at a we were at a cocktail party
the day that I got the car and I was standing
there with Stephen. He was making fun of me and
he says, "You Americans, you're so obsessed with
security. It's a NATO country. What are you so
afraid of?" And they all chuckled. And I said,
"You Brits live in a dream world. If you think
because they have palm trees and pretty beaches
that they're not going to kill you if they have
the chance." And we all laughed again. And then
a couple of weeks later, I made a mistake that
I had never made before. I slept through my
alarm. I had to just get on the main road and
go straight to the embassy. And it was straight
down this direct road called KCS Boulevard. So I
get on QCS to go straight down the mountain
and get to the embassy. Turn on the radio.
I'm listening to some music and this announcer
comes on and he says, "Avoid Kifisias Boulevard.
There was a terrorist attack at Filothei." I had
definitely never heard that, but when he said it,
I see this white this white rover in the far left
lane. There's blood all over the interior of the
windows. And I can see when I get close enough
that the driver side window has been shot out and
Steven Saunders drives a white rover. It turned
out that they had taken him to a hospital that was
next door to the British embassy and he died there
about 20 minutes later. I mean, we knew who did
it. It was revolutionary organization 17 November.
Now, 17 November usually would drop a manifesto at
the site of the of the assassination or they would
mail one to a leftist newspaper. My boss runs into
my office and he says, "Did you see the manifesto
for the Saunders hit?" He says, "It mentions you."
I said, "Come on, not possible." Like seriously,
nobody took security as seriously as I did. And
he shows it to me and it says in Greek, "We saw
the big spy, but he was driving an armored car
and we knew he was armed. So we elected to
carry out the revolutionary sentence on the
war criminal Saunders." And he said, "You got to
go. We're going to take you to the airport. You're
going to go home. We'll pick up your kids. We'll
pick up your wife. We'll pack at your house." So
we flew out. The night before that happened
was the last night I spent in a house with
my wife and we were divorced soon after. She's
just like, "Yeah, I'm not doing this anymore."
Assets are critically important
to counterterrorism because as an
American CIA officer, I'm not going to
be able to infiltrate a group directly.
I was one of only a handful of CIA officers who
spoke fluent Arabic. Even with my fluent Arabic,
I spoke with an accent. So John's not going to
be able to put on a thobe and a dishdasha and
you know walk into a terrorist training camp and
volunteer. That's just not real life. It doesn't
happen. And so your job is to recruit someone
who is either a member of a terrorist group or
can become a member of terrorist group so that
you can use his information to disrupt future
attacks. There are a million different types of
people that you might want to consider recruiting.
But if you recruit a bonafide terrorist, someone
who is able to get into the group, you're going
to meet with him once a month for hours probably,
and he's going to give you five, six, 10 different
intelligence reports. This is what they're talking
about. This is what they're planning. They want to
do an attack in, you know, in Bali or whatever.
That's the stuff that you want to get. When I was
training as a case officer, one of my instructors
said to me that he had gone through his entire 30
plus year career in operations and he never ever
had a target say no to a recruitment. And I said,
"You must be like some kind of a magical wizard
of recruitment." And he laughed and he said, "No,
when you eventually say, listen, I'm not really,
you know, the economic officer here. I'm really
a CIA officer." When you drop that cover, you
have to be certain that they're not going to run
screaming from the room, calling for the police,
reporting you to their ambassador. You're going
to get arrested, you're going to get expelled,
your career is going to come to a halt. You have
to be 100% sure. That's where you take them to
lunch, you take them to dinner, you spend weekends
together, you do day trips, your wives become
friends, your kids are playing together to the
point where you have figured out by now whether he
has a vulnerability. And a vulnerability can mean
a lot of different things. Maybe he just really
really loves his kids. That can be a vulnerability
because then that allows me to say, "I see how
much you love your kids. I know you want your
kids to go to the best schools. I can literally
get your kid into Harvard and I'll pay for it,
too, by the way. And he says, "Well, what do you
want in exchange?" Well, I want the plans to that
new Russian tank. I'd really like to get a peek
at it. Another vulnerability would be, you know,
maybe the guy's wife has cancer, but you can get
her into the Mayo Clinic where she can get the
best cancer treatment on the planet. Maybe the
guy's a drinker or or a gambler, even better,
and he's always short of money because he's maybe
embezzling a little bit from the embassy. 95% of
recruitments are made for the money. Sometimes
it's ideology. Sometimes it's, you know,
this desire for excitement. They love James Bond.
They want to be a part of it. Sometimes it's for
revenge. They hate their boss. They hate their
country. They hate their leader. You've got to
develop that target to the point where he comes
to believe that you are his best friend. To the
point where you know in your heart he's willing to
commit espionage for you. The resources at the CIA
are virtually unlimited. In in exchange though,
the information has to be incredible, let's say.
but you have access to the location of the leader
of al-Qaeda and we're able to break down the door
and grab the guy, there's a reward for you of
between 10 and $25 million that we will pay in
cash, in gold, in diamonds, in land, any way you
want to receive it. But the budget is going to
be there if the information is good. I made a
recruitment one time. I heard from a source a
group of members of a terrorist cell were meeting
for coffee in the same coffee house every single
day 10:00 they'd go for coffee which is a terrible
thing to do by way of of trade craft right never
never establish a pattern I started going there
at 9 9:30 in the morning so sure enough 10 o'clock
they came in four or five of them and one of them
turned and looked at me I did that for a week.
I started the second week. Every day 9:30, I'm
sitting there with my Arabic newspaper. And this
time, one of them nodded at me. So, I nodded back
to him. And then one day, he came in by himself.
And he sits down and we start talking and um and I
ask him if how's his family? Oh, he said, "My wife
is in Cairo with my son and my daughter, and I've
never met my son." He really was a a family man.
He was religious. He made some bad decisions and
ended up in Afghanistan. Then he just wanted to
go home. And I said to him, "If that's if that's
all you want, you just want to go home." I said,
"Well, I can take care of that." To make a long
story short, I recruited him. I got him his
passport. I gave him some money to get himself
established again and put him on a plane and
he gave me in return everything I had asked for.
Very specific information that we used to actively
recruit other al-Qaeda members. I asked him at the
end of it, why did you let me recruit you? And he
said, I've been here for 5 years and you were the
first person who ever asked me about my family.
There are no tactics taught to help you ingratiate
yourself with potential targets. You either have
it in your gut or you don't. So, a normal
asset meeting, you go through the mad minute.
Were you followed here? Were you followed
home last time? Do you have any problems,
any concerns during the course of the month?
and let's meet one month from tonight, you know,
at 8:00 at such and such a hotel. Then you sit
down, you have a coffee, how was your month? How
are things going? What have you heard? What do
you think about this guy? What do you know about
him? Do we need to be worried about him? Is he
in Is he going to be in charge of the weapons
cash? That kind of thing. It's not unusual
for a meeting to last two or three hours.
I was in a meeting once that lasted eight hours.
Could be at a safe house. It can be walking down
the beach, anywhere where you're going to be
safe and that will be private. There was one
source I recruited. It was too dangerous to meet
him in the country that I recruited him in. So we
would fly to Europe and we would meet in Europe
once a month and we would meet like eight hours
a day for 3 days and then I would take a train to
a different country so it didn't look like we were
both flying back from the same city at the same
time and it didn't arouse any suspicion. Yeah.
Some meetings by necessity are conducted in cars
and so sometimes you're going to have to do what's
called a CPU, a car pickup. You want to be able to
pick the person up at a spot whereas few people as
possible are going to see you. Maybe you're doing
it in a semi-residential area where he's standing
on a corner. You come down an alley instead of
a main street. He jumps in the car and you take
off. Let's say the meeting is at 2:00. You want
to be there between 158 and 202. And if you're
there at 158 and he's not there, you do one more
run. And if he's not there by 2002, you abort the
meeting and you try it again 24 hours later or
72 hours later, whatever your agreement is. You
don't want somebody to say, "I wonder why that car
keeps driving in a loop, you know, and then they
write down your license plate number." You just
you don't want to come to anybody's attention.
Double agents are indeed real. Double agents are a
very very big problem on both sides of the double.
I was well into my career and I had a great friend
who was a station chief. He called me one day. I
was at headquarters and he called me from overseas
and he said, "Hey, I was I was hoping you could do
me a favor. One of my guys has recruited a double
agent. The double doesn't know that we know he's
a double. The enemy country has instructed
the double to demand to only speak with the
station chief. And he said, "I live here. It's too
dangerous for me to meet with this guy. Can you
fly out here and pretend to be me and handle the
double agent?" I said, "Of course." So, I fly out
and I meet with the guy. I meet him in some hotel
and I give him a big bear hug at first, which is
unusually warm in the Middle East, but I needed
to pat him down for weapons and he didn't have any
weapons. And so I made a big deal of taking off my
jacket to show him that I didn't have any weapons.
I sat down, we ordered some coffee from room
service. He said, "Are you the chief?" I said,
"You asked for him. You got him, buddy." "I'm
the chief." I would meet with him once a month,
and this went on for about six months. We were
getting, you know, the take on everything that he
was reporting back and what the enemy country was
telling him to do. Finally, I'm at headquarters
one day. I get a call from a sister agency. And
the woman says, "Are you handling this double
case?" And I said, "Yeah, listen. He's been
instructed to kill you in the next meeting."
I said, "Oh, come on." I said, "The guy's afraid
of his shadow. He's not going to kill me. I know
him well. He's a coward. He's not going to pull
a gun and shoot me. But even if he were to pull a
gun and shoot me, how about this? Usually he calls
me when he's coming into the lobby of the hotel,
I'll tell him to come up to the room directly, and
when he comes in, I'll prop the door open. When
he comes in, I'll grab him, take him down, you
guys burst in from the other from the other room,
and we get him. They reluctantly agreed with a
proviso that I wear a bulletproof vest. I said,
"Fine." So, I fly back out and four armed security
guys in the lobby and it turns out the bad guys
have four armed security people in the lobby and
they're all kind of looking at each other sideways
like who are these guys? What's that bulge on that
guy's waist? That kind of thing. And they're all
just kind of standing around staring at each
other. So, he calls me the double and I said,
"Come up to room whatever it is 6:15." He
comes to room 615. I've propped the door
open. He comes in. I tackle him. He's trying to
get the gun out of his waistband. I have his arm,
his hand. My colleagues burst in from the side
and I'm just sitting on him. I have him pinned
down on the floor and I'm sitting on his chest.
In the meantime, he's just like Allah Akbar,
Allah Akbar. And so my liaison partners gave him a
shot of demerol and knocked him out. We put him on
a gurney and covered him up like he was dead and
we put him in the service elevator, took him down,
put him in a an ambulance and we took him to
intelligence service headquarters. He woke up
two hours later tied to a chair. I said, "We can
do it the easy way. We can do it the hard way. It
totally up to you. we know who you are. He was the
leader of that country's Hezbollah wing. I said,
"We want all the weapons, all of them. We know
that you're the keeper of the weapons." He's like,
"Fuck you." So, I said to liaison, "We should just
break into his house. I mean, there's a there's
a good chance all these weapons are just in his
house." And they said, "We can't. He's got a he's
got a a live-in maid and she doesn't know anything
and she never ever leaves the house. And I said,
"Okay, well, let's just declare a gas leak
in the neighborhood and then we'll evacuate
the cul-de-sac and then we'll just go in. Bring a
locks and picks team in and just pick the lock."
They said, "No, we can't do that. We don't have
we don't have gas lines in this country. We use
propane. Bring a propane truck. We'll leak the
propane. Then we'll just declare the emergency."
The fire department comes. They evacuate all of
the six houses. We break into his house and we
find a safe, like a double size gun safe. It was
enormous. The biggest gun safe I've ever seen.
The weapons have to be in there. So, we bring
the locks and picks team in and they've got,
you know, the stethoscope on and they're
doing the tumbler and they crack the safe.
They open it and it's empty except for this
handwritten like childlike handwritten map.
So, we get in these two jeeps. We drive south as
the map tells us to do. We get out where it tells
us to get out. And we found this bunker full to
the to the ceiling with every weapon they had,
landmines, hand grenades, rocket propelled
grenades, everything they had. We completely put
Hezbollah out of business in that country. And as
it turns out, he's still in prison 25 years later.
And SDR is a surveillance detection route. This
is something that literally every CIA officer must
be trained in. This is what's going to keep you
from being assassinated or arrested. And so you
leave what's called your kickoff point. It could
be home, the office, wherever you happen to be.
You'll do one that's maybe two hours. is if you're
in a very hostile place, your SDR could be eight
hours. You're changing into pre-positioned cars,
you're taking the subway, then you're walking,
then you get in a different car, maybe you take
an Uber for a little bit of it. An SDR comes in
four different phases. The kickoff phase, you just
go from from your kickoff to point A, and then you
do kind of a it's called a stair step. make a
right, a left, a right, a left, a right, a left
to go to your next stop, which is maybe, you know,
it's a fabric store. When you're stair-stepping
like that, you can definitely see if you're
being followed. If you're being followed,
you abort the meeting and you just drive home
and you do the whole thing again 24 hours later.
If you are not sure you're being followed,
you enter what's called the provocative phase
where you'll drive halfway up a block, then make a
U-turn and drive back. Make a K-turn, drive back,
pull into another driveway, make a K-turn. Stuff
that doesn't make any sense at all. But that's
just to make sure with 100% certainty that you're
not being followed. I served overseas with a with
a woman who was a legitimate State Department
officer. She came into the office one day and
she said, "Oh, I was under heavy surveillance
last night. I took them on a ride that they'll
never forget. I was going 100 miles an hour down
the highway and I'm just sitting there listening
because what happened was they determined
that because she tried so hard to lose them,
she must be the CIA officer." And so they never
ever surveilled me because I'm going to the wine
store and going to the fabric store and then I'm
driving home. but they were plenty interested
in her. You have to be very very careful not to
establish patterns and I almost got myself burned
twice. So there was one there was one point where
I was flying to Eastern Europe once a month to
handle an asset that I had recruited. He was very
proud of the village that he had come from. It was
high up in the mountains and there was a hunting
lodge up there. He said, "Let's go to this hunting
lodge. I remember it so fondly from my childhood.
And they serve wild boar and they serve bear stew
and all kinds of crazy stuff. So I went with him.
I ordered a very unusual drink which I shouldn't
have but it was something my grandmother used to
drink and I remembered it from my childhood and he
was talking about his childhood. So I ordered the
drink and the waitress brought it to me. The next
month I flew up to see him and he said, "Let's go
to the hunting lodge again. They have venison this
time of the year and it's really amazing. So,
we drive to Honey Lodge and I order the drink,
the same drink, and the waitress says, "I remember
you." And I said, "No, no, I don't think so. I've
never been here before." And she said, "Yes, you
have. You're the only person who's ever ordered
that drink, and I've been here for 10 years." I
said, "Oh, that's right. I was here once before."
It's like, "Dog gone it." she spotted me. Now,
she was just a waitress, but what if she had been
an intelligence officer posing as a waitress? Or
what if she was a police informant who's going to
now rat me out to the local cops that I'm meeting
with this, you know, this guy? And so afterwards,
I said, "I am so sorry. I blew it. We can never
ever go back there again." And we never did.
In January of 2002, I was named chief of CIA
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan and
there was a flood of al-Qaeda fighters across
the border into Pakistan. So I went out and I
came up with this idea that instead of trying
to catch them in these forbidding mountains,
we'll catch five, 10, 20 at a time in the safe
houses. So that's the practice that we adopted.
And then after I had been in Pakistan about six
weeks, we got word that Abu Zubaydah was somewhere
in Pakistan. We thought at the time wrongly that
Abu Zubaydah was the number three in al-Qaeda.
If you wanted to be smuggled into Afghanistan to
make jihad, he would smuggle you in. And finally,
I asked headquarters to send a friend of mine out.
He was a a targeting analyst, somebody who pours
through millions of bits of data to try to isolate
the location of one person. I said, "Buddy,
we're on the trail of Abu Zubaydah." And I said,
"But he's right ahead of us. We just can't catch
him." Like sometimes we'd break down a door and
there's a cigarette that's still lit. So I said,
"You've got to you got to pin this down for me. We
just can't find him." Finally, he came to me and
he said, "I can't get it down to any fewer than
14 sites." I said, '14 sites. We've never done
more than two raids in a single night before.
Like, this doesn't really help. So, I cabled
headquarters and I said, "We're going to need
a big team." I asked for 36 people. I asked for
a pallet of weapons and ammunition and cash and
night vision goggles and more battering rams and
you name it. And then the next day, a colleague
of mine and two Pakistani officers started going
from sight to sight to look at all 14 sites. We
wanted to make sure we weren't driving into an
ambush. Do they know we're coming tonight? Most
of these places were little hovels, little one
room shacks made of concrete block or corrugated
tin. It was miserable. We come out of the back
end of the University of Faisalabad and there's
this enormous yellow house which corresponds with
site 12 and my Pakistani counterpart said I can
tell you right now something bad is happening in
there. He said it's 100° right now and all their
shutters are closed. They have to be broiling in
there but they want people to think there's
nobody home. We caught dozens and dozens of
people crammed into that house. We're going to
the last site and the analyst calls me and he
says Abu Zubaydah just made a terrible mistake.
He accessed his emails from a landline. I said,
"Oh my god, and the landline is associated with
an address." And he says, "And it's site 13."
I still have chills thinking about it. And I
said, I we got him. So, we drive to site 13,
but it's an empty field. I said, how can this
be? We're sure that he's here, but there's no
house here. It's just an empty field. And
the Pakistani major laughs, and he says,
now this happens all the time. He calls a young
technical officer, climbs the pole, goes through
this head of wires, finds the wire, follows
it down the pole, down the alley, and he says,
"It's that house right there." We all gathered.
It was like 60, 70 of us, Pakistanis, FBI, CIA,
we all gathered at the safe house. I stood on the
coffee table and I said, "Okay, so rule number
one, we have to take him alive." And exactly
as the clock strikes two, break down the door,
separate the women and children from the men and
take all the men to the Faisalabad jail. And so at
2 a.m. I was on the roof of the safe house with
my buddy. And I looked at my watch and I said,
"O200, here we go." And then we hear gunshots and
I said, "That's not good." We jump into our car.
We speed over to site 13 and there are three
people laying in the street. One is obviously
dead. One looks like he's dead or he's going to be
dead pretty soon. And the other one is screaming
bloody murder. So I said, "What happened?" And
this Pakistani policeman says, "We got him. We
got your man." and he points at the guy who's
like almost dead. I didn't have time to scream
at this guy that the order was to take him alive.
What happened was Abu Zubaydah, a Syrian bomber,
and Abu Zubaydah's bodyguard climbed to the roof
of the safe house and were jumping to the roof of
the neighboring house to try to escape. And this
Pakistani policeman was just picking them off as
they were jumping. And he shot Abu Zubaydah three
times in the thigh, the groin, and the stomach.
So, I said, "This doesn't look anything like our
target." We had a six-year-old passport photo. So,
I called the analyst. I said, "Listen, I don't
know if it's him." He said, "Give me a shot of
his eye. I'll run a retinal scan." So, I lifted up
his eye. And it was rolled back in his head. All
you could see was white. He's bleeding to death.
All I get are the whites of his eyes. He said,
"Get me his ear. Take a picture of his ear."
I didn't know that no two people on Earth have
the same ears until that night. They're like
fingerprints. So I take a picture of the ear
headquarters says it's him. So we pick him up,
throw him in the back of this pickup truck,
speed to Faisalabad Hospital. So they rush him
into surgery. But word got around the al-Qaeda
community that we had gotten him. And so they
started driving by the hospital and just opening
fire on the hospital. We kept diving down. I
said to the Pakistani major that I was with,
"If they realize how lightly armed we are, we're
dead." I said, "Can you get a helicopter in here?"
20 minutes later, a helicopter lands in the
parking lot. I walk into the to the operating
room with like this with my shirt up over my
nose. I said, "Doc, wrap it up. We have to
go." We put him on the helicopter. Like four
of us got onto the helicopter and we flew to
a Pakistani military base about 50 miles away.
And the doctor there said he had never seen a
patient with wounds so severe who lived. But
he lived and sure enough it took a little
while but Abu Zubaydah started to open up and
the information that he gave was actionable.
The way we prepared for raids in Pakistan was
actually quite simple. I went online with my
CIA credit card and I bought everything I needed.
I brought battering rams and bulletproof vests,
weapons and ammunition and walkie-talkies and you
name it. We didn't have gear that I think most
people would consider to be sophisticated. We all
had 9 mm, just 9 millimeters because they're so
reliable. We all had bulletproof vests. A couple
of the guys had helmets, not many. Lots and lots
and lots of ammunition. And that was pretty much
it. We got a tip with an address. We had two CIA
officers, two FBI agents, and two Pakistani
officials. And we went at two o'clock in the
morning. Counted one, two, three, boom, with
a battering ram, bust the door down, throw in
a flashbang grenade just to scare everybody and
make them disoriented. And we grabbed these two
kids. They 18, 19 years old. They both burst into
tears. And so we got a tip later in the week from
a friendly Arab intelligence officer. So we did it
again and we caught some serious people the second
time. A relatively senior member of Egyptian
Islamic Jihad and some al-Qaeda like mid-level
al-Qaeda fighters. We did it at 2 am because like
literally everybody in Pakistan sound asleep at 2
am. It's like they just they just close the
country. There's no traffic. There's nobody
out there. Everybody's asleep. And so we figured
that was our best chance of not getting caught.
I did dozens of interrogations when I was in
Pakistan and I was always the good cop. It
was always easier for me, more natural. And the
Pakistanis because it was their country and their
rules are different than ours, they could be the
bad cop. So the very first interrogation I did was
of a Jordanian prisoner. They brought him in and
we chained him to an eyebolt in the in the table
and I said, "I'm from the American government and
I want to ask you some questions." And he says,
"Very well." Then I laid out a map of the Afghan
Pakistan border and I told him with his finger to
show me exactly how he crossed the border. We knew
how they were crossing the border. We called them
rat lines. We knew where the rat lines were. but
he told me the truth and I thought, you know what,
this actually works. And so we brought in the
next prisoner. Now, there were some that had
read the al-Qaeda training manual, not knowing
that I had also read it. And so, they're like,
you know, they they pretend to pass out and
they just fall off the chair and you're just
sitting there and then like they're laying on
the ground, they open one eye and you're like,
get back on the chair. What's the matter with you?
And then they get up back and sit on the chair
and then they oh they go oh like this stomach pain
and you're like buddy I read the al-Qaeda training
manual. I know all the different things you're
going to try to do. And then they just won't
answer any questions. So we send him back to the
jail. The ones that were cooperative for the most
part ended up being released. Some were held for
a while in Pakistan. Then they were expelled, sent
back to their home country. But the ones who were
uncooperative from Pakistan went to Guantanamo.
My conversations with Abu Zubaydah were generally
not substantive. After 56 hours, the CIA sent in
a private jet with a trauma surgeon from John's
Hopkins University Medical Center. He flew out
to the base. They picked up Abu Zubaydah and
they took him to the first of about a half a
dozen secret sites. They took him all over the
world just to make sure that the flight couldn't
be traced. So he arrived at the secret site and
was given six weeks to recover from his gunshot
wounds. And so after 6 weeks he was he was well
enough to be interrogated. So an FBI agent by the
name of Ali Soufan began interrogating him. in
that FBI way where you treat people with respect
and establish this rapport. Maybe you offer him
a cigarette or an orange or a cup of tea or if
he's really really helpful, you let him write a
letter to his parents or whatever. And sometimes
that takes days, weeks, months, whatever.
But they always open up. And sure enough,
it took a little while a number of weeks, but
Abu Zubaydah started to open up and everything
that he gave Ali was true and it was actionable.
For example, we didn't have any idea what the
al-Qaeda wiring diagram looked like. This sounds
nuts now, but in the immediate aftermath of 9/11,
we didn't know what this al-Qaeda really was. The
other thing he told us was even more important.
So Abu Zubaydah told us about Khalid
Sheikh Mohammed. We had never heard the
name before and we were able to focus all of our
counterterrorism assets just to find Khalid Shake
Muhammad and we found him. It took us another
year but we found him. 911 was still an open,
fresh criminal investigation. And so, you
know, the FBI needed to be interrogating
these prisoners. And the CIA resented that
we were overseas and the FBI was in charge
of the interrogation because the traditional
relationship is that the CIA is always in charge
overseas. The CIA insisted that it be them.
And so the CIA was not willing to be patient.
They picked up Abu Zubaydah and they took him
to the first of about a half a dozen secret
sites where he underwent merciless torture. And
we have nothing to show for it. Torture is the
worst possible interrogation technique. It does
not work. Yes. Eventually, the prisoner is going
to tell you what you want to know or what he
thinks you want to hear. But there's so much
garbage that's thrown in with that. It's going
to take your analysts months to pour through the
information to see what's real, what's not real,
and by then, you know, the bomb has already gone
off or the the operation has already taken place
and, you know, you've just cost more American
lives. Torture is not appropriate under any
circumstances. We caught a guy in Pakistan and we
sent him off to be tortured. And I start getting
these hair on fire cables from the secret site
saying, "Here's an address in Quetta. It's the big
al-Qaeda safe house. You have to go raid it." And
we bust down the door in the middle of the night
and it's just some old lady living in her house.
Then we get another hair on fire cable saying
there's a weapons cache and it's buried next
to this building in Peshawar and here's the
address and we go and it's it's a shish kebab
restaurant and we've got you know metal detectors
and ground penetrating radar and there's nothing
buried there at all. The Senate Select Committee
on Intelligence Majority Staff decided to do a
complete and comprehensive study on the CIA's
torture program, which of course the CIA called
enhanced interrogation techniques. They ended up
writing a 5,000page report that is so damning and
so highly classified that all that was released
was a very heavily redacted copy of the 500page
executive summary of the report. And so the CIA
essentially admits that it came up with a torture
program. It paid handsomely for the torture
program. It implemented the torture program. When
I returned from Pakistan, I was asked by a CTC
colleague if I wanted to be, his words, certified
in the use of in the use of enhanced interrogation
techniques. I had never heard that term before. So
I said, "That sounds like a torture program." He
said, "It's not a torture program. DOJ approved
it and the president signed it." I said, "This
is a torture program and I don't want anything
to do with it." I was the only one who said
no. That conversation about torture bothered
me very deeply. And then I got passed over for
promotion. I just captured Abu Zubaydah with
these two hands. And we still thought at the time
he was the number three. And I got passed over
for promotion. I went into my boss's office. I was
screaming. And he said, "In your promotion panel,
the director said that you displayed a shocking
lack of commitment to counterterrorism." I said,
"Because I won't torture people." Well, I was
also friendly with the deputy director of the
CIA and he came up to me. He came up to me
one day and he said, he goes like this, "Your
name wasn't on the list." I said, "You believe
it?" And he promoted me with a stroke of a pen,
which was incredibly generous. And then I
went on to my next assignment after that.
I resigned from the CIA a year later, went
into the private sector, and I just, I thought,
you know, this torture program is so wrong and so
illegal. Somebody's going to say something to the
media, and nobody did. And then in December of
2007, ABC News called me. I had never spoken to
a journalist before. He had a source who said that
I had tortured Abu Zubaydah. I said, "Absolutely
untrue. I was the only person who was kind to Abu
Zubaydah. I'll give you your interview. And so we
met up at ABC News studios in Washington. I said
that the CIA was torturing its prisoners. I said
that torture was the official policy of the US
government. It was not the result of a rogue.
And I said that the policy had been personally
approved by the president. I am very sorry to
tell you that Abu Zubaydah is still in Guantanamo
today. This is a man who has been in American
custody now for almost 24 years. He's never
been accused of a crime, let alone convicted of
one. And according to the Senate torture report,
quoting the CIA, he will never be freed. And when
he dies, he'll be cremated and his ashes thrown
into the Caribbean. It's un-American. I've been
in touch with his attorneys and they continue to
be slightly hopeful that the political tide will
eventually change and somebody in the White House
is going to do the right thing. I hope that's
the case. I think he should have been released
many years ago when we first realized that this
was not the number three in al-Qaeda, that he had
never committed a crime against Americans. He had
never joined al-Qaeda. And even if he had founded
the House of Martyrs safe house and the Kandahar
and Helmand training camps, he's paid for those
crimes many times over. He should be released.
The CIA reported me to the FBI for revealing
classified information. They investigated me
for three more years. I had no idea
my emails were being intercepted.
teams of FBI agents were conducting surveillance
on me. And then I was arrested in January of 2012
and charged with five felonies, including three
counts of espionage. So, I was facing 45 years
in prison. The government offered me 30 months,
of which I would do 23. And then the whole thing
would go away. My lawyers told me that this could
be a blip in my life or it could be the defining
event in my life. Make it the blip. My wife and
I stayed up all night long and I said, "By God,
I haven't done anything wrong. I'm not going to
take it." The lawyers were so mad. They came to my
house 7:00 in the morning and he said, "You know
what your problem is? Your problem is you think
this is about justice and it's not about justice.
It's about mitigating damage. take the deal. And I
said, "If I don't take the deal and I'm convicted,
what am I realistically looking at?" And he said,
"12 to 18 years. Take the deal." And so I took the
deal. The the sad irony, I would even call it the
sick irony of this whole story, is that I'm the
only person who had any connection whatsoever with
the CIA's torture program, who went to prison.
Not because I tortured anybody, but because I blew
the whistle on it. The people who came up with
the torture are free and rich, I might add. The
people who approved the torture are free and rich.
The people who carried out the torture are free.
The people who covered up the torture are free. I
was the only one who went to prison. And honestly,
I wouldn't change anything. I'm on the
right side of history, and they are not.
I started working for the CIA on January the
7th, 1990. And my first job there was in an
office. It was to be an analyst. I got bored with
analysis in 1997. And so I decided to make a very
unusual switch to counterterrorism operations. A
counterterrorism ops position opened where they
were looking for an officer who spoke either
Greek or Arabic. It turned out that I was the
only person in the entire CIA who spoke both
Greek and Arabic. They decided that it was a
lot cheaper and a lot easier to take a linguist
and teach him operations. So I got the job. Then
you start the basic training on how to recruit
spies to steal secrets. And you go to training at
what's called the farm, which is the CIA's famed
training center. The first thing I did was a class
that we called crash and bang. It was literally
crashing cars through roadblocks or having your
instructors shooting at your car with, you know,
paint pellets and you rolling out of the passenger
door and opening fire on a robot that's firing at
you from a van. The bang part was learning how to
use weapons. the Glock 9 millimeter semi-automatic
handgun, the Smith and Wesson 38 revolver,
the Remington pump-action 12 gauge. We fired tens
of thousands of rounds and really became experts
in these things. It was a lot of fun. And then you
go into these other courses, things like defensive
driving, counterterrorist driving, surveillance,
and surveillance detection. And then I went on
to my assignment in Greece. I was halfway into my
tour in Athens when I received a cable inviting me
to apply for acceptance to a new training course
called advanced counterterrorism operations and I
jumped at it. So I flew back to the states took
six weeks and it was like in-depth high threat
high danger counterterrorism operations. Then we
started doing things like beacons for example or
listening devices or covert video or you know we
were just starting with this notion of drones.
It was all brand new. The driving portion
was more about crashing through roadblocks,
crashing through cars. I got injured in that
training. I mean this is this is serious. If
you're if you're in some island in the southern
Philippines and the al-Qaeda people down there
are trying to stop you and they've got two cars
blocking the road and you've got to crash through,
you have to know which part of the car to crash
through. For example, if they're just like this,
right? The engine's too heavy. You're going to
kill yourself if you crash into the engine. So,
you crash through the trunk, it pushes the
car out of the way, and you are able to drive
off. You learn little things like the very first
thing I do when I get in my car and I still do it
to this day is I lock the doors before I even put
the key in the ignition. I lock the doors because
in training they have you blindfolded and then
they lift the blindfold off and you have three
seconds to respond to whatever it is you see
in front of you. It might be a roadblock. It
might be a guy standing with an AK-47 in front
of you, or it might be a guy opening your door
very quietly to put a 9 millimeter at your head
and say, "Bang, you're dead. You fail." And then
you have to do the whole thing over again. So,
you learn all these different techniques. They
sent us out to Utah and then Nevada and we just
drove through the desert over sand dunes and,
you know, how not to get stuck. Then we were on
a track, you know, 60 miles an hour backwards
and spinning around. We learned how to do pit
maneuvers, but it's a lot of hands-on stuff.
You you're pretty banged up. Everybody had
whiplash when we finished. And I had to have
my right knee replaced what we do for our country.
So they prepared me for everything. In retrospect,
nothing could possibly have better prepared me
for 9/11 in Pakistan. I had been in Greece for
a couple of months and I had bought a 50-inch
TV. So, I had the TV on the back seat of my
BMW 540, my armored BMW. I noticed that there was
a motorcyclist to my right and he was trying very
hard to stay in my blind spot. When I slow down,
he slows down. When I speed up, he speeds up. I'm
a little nervous. So, I unzipped my fanny pack so
that my gun was easier to get and I slowed down.
He slowed down. I decided to slam on the brakes
and try to hit the guy. But he was good. So,
I hit the brakes. I swerve to the right. He
swerves to the right. I miss him. I speed up.
He speeds up. I swerve to hit him a couple of
times again and I couldn't hit him. But then
it's Athens, which is famous for its traffic.
So, we come to this intersection. It's like
a major intersection. It's 12 lanes, if you can
imagine. And it's just jammed full of traffic. So,
I'm stuck. I pull out my gun. I'm starting to
kind of panic inside myself, not thinking. I'm
in an armored car. Just crash the cars out of
out of the way. That's what you're trained to
do. But I'm going to like I'm prepared to get out
and shoot the guy. He gets off the motorcycle. He
reaches into his waistband and he pulls out what
looked to me like a 38. It was a smallal-ish gun.
It may have been a 22, but it looked like a
38. I saw a path to escape. And so I gunned
it. I crashed the motorcycle. The motorcycle
just goes flying and I take off up GCS. So I
got to the cops and they found the motorcycle.
It turned out the license plate had been stolen.
Then the question is, was this a an attempted
terrorist attack? We went out to literally every
single one of our counterterrorism sources.
None of them knew anything. And in the end,
and it was a weeks long investigation, they
determined that it was it was an attempted
carjacking. It was a thief who saw this at the
time state-of-the-art gigantic TV on the back of
a of a BMW. And he thought, I'm going to carjack
this guy and take his car and his TV. But it also
put me in a frame of mind to be more wary. And so
when I got to Pakistan, I was much quicker to act.
I really believe that the future of
counterterrorism is a combination of human
intelligence and drones to infiltrate terrorist
groups. Though the drone's not going to collect
the information. You know, these bad guys, they
exercise electronic discipline. They're not going
to say the plans for the next terrorist attack are
going to be this, you know, on the phone. You need
human beings inside these groups to figure out
what exactly they're planning to do. But then
when it comes time to confront them, I think we're
very quickly getting to a point where you're not
going to see CIA officers on the ground with M4s
and bulletproof vests and helmets parachuting
out of planes. It's going to be drones with
Hellfire missiles attached to their undersides.
I'm worried about AI vis-a-vis counterterrorism.
First of all, it's tough enough as it is to cross
borders with six different identities, right?
How in the world are CIA officers going to
cross borders or get through airports with
facial recognition scans and AI, you know,
following their every movement around the world.
At the same time, AI makes the bad guys smarter.
So CIA's got the money and they have access to the
right people and the right companies and the right
experts to stay up on this. But this is this is
going to be an uphill struggle. The international
terrorism landscape changes constantly. There
are some constants in that landscape like ISIS
or any of its variations. And then there are
both al-Qaeda and ISIS groups that have popped
up individually in northern Pakistan, in India,
in the Philippines, all over the place. It's
like playing whack-a-ole where just as you destroy
one, another one pops up that you have to bash in
the head, too. I think we should be choosing our
battles carefully. We shouldn't be casting such
a wide net. There's something recent that that
bothers me greatly and that is the government's
decision to expand the definition of a terrorist
group. Right? There's a pretty easy definition of
terrorism. It is using violence to put forward
a political goal. They're adding groups to the
terrorism watch list that have never been on the
terrorism watch list any before. groups that are
loosely associated with what is called Antifa
being added to the list is just silly to me.
First of all, Antifa is not a group. It's an idea.
It doesn't have a headquarters. They don't issue
membership cards. They're just loosely affiliated
people who are anti-fascist. I would posit that
every soldier and seller who participated in D-Day
was anti-fascist. They would be Antifa. So, that's
just silly to me. To me, that's a mistake because
it diverts attention and it diverts finances. We
should be focused on the groups that mean us harm,
real harm. We should be out there trying to hunt
down the people who have taken an oath to kill
Americans. So, I'm worried that that it's too easy
now to describe people as terrorists. I disagree
with President Trump's decision to declare the
narco groups in Mexico and elsewhere in Latin
America as terrorist groups. At first, I thought
that he did that solely for legalistic reasons
because it would it would serve to free up budgets
and it would also authorize NSA to begin wiretaps
or interceptions of the cartels communications,
which is awesome, great. but declaring them
terrorist groups other than them allowing the
Pentagon to drone their boats, which may or may
not be their boats. I think it's misguided. I'm
more of a civil libertarian in this respect in
that if these people are so dangerous and have
committed such terrible crimes against the United
States, charge them with a crime. You can't just
not like somebody's face so you fly around the
world to kill them. We're a nation of laws and we
should abide by those laws. So Anwar Al-Aulaqi,
for example, the spokesman for al-Qaeda,
guy's an American citizen, born and raised in New
Mexico, self-radicalizes, joins al-Qaeda as their
spokesman. We blew him up with a drone. He had
never been charged with any crime. If he was as
bad as you say he was, you at the CIA, then have
the Justice Department file a charge against him.
But you can't just go around the world murdering
people whose politics you don't like and still
profess to be this beacon of, you know, respect
for human rights. I like to consider myself a
realist. If I had my way about it, I would tear
the CIA down to the bare studs and maybe rebuild
it, but as a shell of what it is today. But I know
that's not going to happen. And so it's up to the
rest of us through our elected officials to make
sure that the CIA remain law-abiding or become
law-abiding. Besides that, I often encourage
young people to apply to the CIA. You can
actually affect change from the inside. And I know
that's how if there's going to be change, that's
how it's going to be. It's going to come from the
inside. [Producer] If people want to find more of
your work, where can they find you? My first seven
books were about the CIA. I have several podcasts.
I have one called John Kiriakou's Dead Drop. I
have one called Deep Focus with John Kiriakou.
That's on YouTube. And then I'm starting a
nationwide speaking tour. I had a successful
speaking tour around England, Scotland, Wales.
So, we're going to do it here in the States.
Hi, I'm a producer on authorized
account. If you enjoyed this video,
then please subscribe and comment with more
topics that you'd like us to cover in this series.